<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word of information &amp; advice touching tythes, and other the goods appropriate (as yet left) to Church-men. Wherein is given a hint of the light and knowledg of God and his mind touching these things, as they have been from the beginnging almost till now. / Humbly presented by R.B. of N.W. to the governors of this commonwealth.</title>
            <author>R. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E671_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207078</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76343)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E671[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word of information &amp; advice touching tythes, and other the goods appropriate (as yet left) to Church-men. Wherein is given a hint of the light and knowledg of God and his mind touching these things, as they have been from the beginnging almost till now. / Humbly presented by R.B. of N.W. to the governors of this commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>R. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop at the black spread Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from the colophon.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 21.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166236:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A WORD OF Information &amp; Advice TOUCHING TYTHES, And other the <hi>Goods Appropriate</hi> (as yet left) to <hi>Church-men.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein is given a Hint of the Light and Knowledg of God and his Mind touching theſe things, as they have been from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning almoſt till now.</head>
            <byline>Humbly preſented by <hi>R. B.</hi> of <hi>N. W.</hi> to the <hi>Governors</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </byline>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Bſerving what <hi>ado</hi> there is in the <hi>Land</hi> as touching <hi>theſe things,</hi> I have alſo <hi>judg'd</hi> it <hi>meet</hi> to give my <hi>advice,</hi> for the <hi>Peace ſake</hi> and <hi>good</hi> of <hi>men:</hi> That I might make out my mind in <hi>brief,</hi> I would firſt give <hi>notice</hi> according to the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Scripture of Truth,</hi> that there are in the world <hi>now,</hi> as there were <hi>heretofore,</hi> theſe <hi>three ranks</hi> or <hi>degrees</hi> of men; the <hi>firſt were</hi> and <hi>are</hi> ſuch that <hi>live wholy alienated</hi> from the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>true</hi> knowledg of <hi>God,</hi> being in <hi>continual, open,</hi> and <hi>manifeſt rebellion,</hi> in <hi>heart, thought,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:166236:2"/>
and <hi>life</hi> againſt <hi>him;</hi> ſuch were the moſt of the <hi>Gentiles hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> and there be not a <hi>few</hi> of the like <hi>ſpirit</hi> found among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that <hi>yet profeſs</hi> the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Chriſt now,</hi> yea the <hi>multitude</hi> of all <hi>Lands</hi> are ſuch: theſe <hi>people</hi> have, as <hi>open</hi> and profeſt <hi>Rebels,</hi> or like high-way <hi>theeves, taken all</hi> they <hi>ever</hi> can <hi>lay hands on,</hi> and <hi>together</hi> with <hi>themſelves beſtow all</hi> upon <hi>their lusts,</hi> which are indeed the <hi>alone gods</hi> they <hi>ſerve,</hi> which were <hi>noted</hi> among the <hi>Heathen</hi> under the <hi>names</hi> either of <hi>Mars,</hi> as the <hi>god</hi> of <hi>ſome,</hi> or <hi>Bacchus</hi> the <hi>god</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> the <hi>god</hi> or <hi>goddeſs</hi> of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All</hi> which, and their <hi>mind,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle comprehends</hi> in that <hi>ſaying, Their god is their belly, their glory is their ſhame, they mind</hi> (and <hi>nothing elſe</hi> but) <hi>earthly things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Wherefore in the ſecond <hi>place,</hi> it being <hi>now</hi> in a <hi>manner</hi> fully in the <hi>heart</hi> of man, that as for the moſt <hi>holy, high,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed God</hi> (who is alſo <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Gods,</hi> the <hi>fountain</hi> and <hi>first riſe</hi> of <hi>all good) he</hi> had indeed <hi>forſaken</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>left man</hi> to take his <hi>paſtime here,</hi> and to <hi>do</hi> his <hi>own will,</hi> and what <hi>liked</hi> him <hi>beſt,</hi> every one <hi>following</hi> the <hi>imagination</hi> of his own <hi>heart,</hi> it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> for a <hi>remembrance</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> in all <hi>ages</hi> to <hi>reſerve</hi> a <hi>people,</hi> which he hath <hi>always</hi> made <hi>ready,</hi> and <hi>prepared</hi> for <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> in the <hi>furnace</hi> of <hi>affliction,</hi> as he did the <hi>remnant</hi> of the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> theſe are the <hi>ſecond ſort</hi> of <hi>people,</hi> that in their <hi>affliction,</hi> through the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>indwelling,</hi> and <hi>clear opening</hi> of the <hi>Grace of God</hi> unto them <hi>therein,</hi> are made willing to <hi>become tributary</hi> to <hi>God; theſe,</hi> that he might <hi>bind</hi> them <hi>faſt to himſelf,</hi> according as they were <hi>capable,</hi> he <hi>made</hi> with them <hi>ſome Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>Covenant, thereby preſerving</hi> them in ſome <hi>way</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> of <hi>ſubjection to,</hi> and <hi>acknowledgment of him,</hi> as their <hi>liege Lord</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> whoſe <hi>they,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> that <hi>they had,</hi> by <hi>right,</hi> the <hi>highest right</hi> of <hi>all, was; only</hi> becauſe of their <hi>weakneſs,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs, wholy</hi> and in all <hi>points</hi> to <hi>give up themſelves</hi> to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together at the <hi>dispoſe</hi> of this their <hi>ſupream Soveraign, King,</hi> and <hi>Lord;</hi> he <hi>humbled himſelf,</hi> and <hi>condeſcended</hi> for a <hi>while</hi> and <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to <hi>take</hi> of them only ſome <hi>remembrances,</hi> as ſome part of their <hi>time,</hi> as one <hi>day</hi> in <hi>ſeven,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>whole,</hi> and ſo ſome <hi>part</hi> of their <hi>Corn, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Oyl,</hi> and all that they <hi>had,</hi> and did put their hands <hi>unto:</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> he took by <hi>Commandment</hi> only the <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Offerings,</hi> yet of theſe <hi>things</hi> he took ſo <hi>great</hi> a <hi>ſhare,</hi> that he <hi>ſeemed</hi> indeed to <hi>oppreſs them more</hi> then any other <hi>people</hi> were, that they might be <hi>thought</hi> to have more <hi>cauſe</hi> to complain for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166236:2"/>
this <hi>matter,</hi> then <hi>any</hi> have upon <hi>any</hi> the <hi>like,</hi> or the <hi>pretended like</hi> to the <hi>ſame now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Of this <hi>ſecond ſort</hi> of <hi>people</hi> there is in <hi>this,</hi> and in <hi>other Countries, ſome,</hi> or <hi>rather</hi> a very great <hi>remembrance,</hi> whoſe <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> were it in <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>ſo far</hi> as <hi>ſo it is,</hi> is <hi>far</hi> more <hi>excellent</hi> then the <hi>former,</hi> and <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>had</hi> in <hi>eſteem</hi> above <hi>them,</hi> even as <hi>ſubjects</hi> that acknowledg their <hi>Soveraign Prince,</hi> are <hi>above thoſe</hi> that are in <hi>open</hi> and <hi>profeſt rebellion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>him;</hi> hence it is they are <hi>zealous</hi> ſome <hi>more</hi> according to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſome upon the <hi>account</hi> as well of <hi>Tradition</hi> as the <hi>Scripture,</hi> for <hi>neither</hi> in their <hi>place</hi> ought to be had in <hi>contempt,</hi> or which to ſay is <hi>better, both having respect</hi> to the <hi>Scripture;</hi> but ſome take <hi>leſs,</hi> ſome more <hi>example</hi> from the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> as thoſe we call the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> yea and ſome of the <hi>Proteſtants too,</hi> as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> beyond the <hi>Seas,</hi> and the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops heretofore</hi> in this <hi>Land,</hi> the <hi>Anceſtors</hi> of <hi>theſe,</hi> ſith they were <hi>not able</hi> to go <hi>forward</hi> to the <hi>purity, holineſs, divinity,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-denyal</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> went <hi>back again</hi> to the <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> I mean to <hi>many</hi> of <hi>them (doubtleſs</hi> of a <hi>good mind</hi> in <hi>ſome</hi>) who not <hi>being able</hi> to <hi>keep</hi> their <hi>ground</hi> in <hi>Grace,</hi> or in the <hi>Gospel</hi> or <hi>new Law, took</hi> up their <hi>ſtation</hi> in the <hi>Old,</hi> or the <hi>things</hi> in <hi>uſe,</hi> through the <hi>Command</hi> of it, though <hi>many</hi> have ſince in a <hi>great degree</hi> been <hi>beaten off it,</hi> and are <hi>faln back</hi> into the <hi>dark Hell</hi> and <hi>Abyſs</hi> of <hi>Evil,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Gentiliſm, wherein even Abraham</hi> was before he <hi>beleeved:</hi> Yet even this <hi>Gentiliſm</hi> hath for it a <hi>double vail,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> more <hi>thick</hi> and <hi>manifeſt,</hi> as that of the <hi>Old Law,</hi> the other being <hi>ſcarce</hi> any other then the very <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. But there are a <hi>ſecond ſort,</hi> which would <hi>ſeem,</hi> and <hi>indeed</hi> in ſome <hi>ſort</hi> are, more <hi>Reformed,</hi> as the <hi>followers</hi> of <hi>Calvin,</hi> whom yet many have <hi>clouded,</hi> he being far more in the <hi>light</hi> then thoſe that <hi>ſeem</hi> to be ſo great <hi>admirers</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> who <hi>pretend</hi> to l t <hi>go</hi> what the <hi>others keep cloſe</hi> to, the many <hi>uſages</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations</hi> of the <hi>old Law,</hi> and to <hi>aſpire to,</hi> and abide <hi>in,</hi> the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>freedom</hi> of the <hi>New,</hi> only here in <hi>England,</hi> is made a <hi>double reſerve,</hi> the one of a <hi>ſeventh day Sabbath,</hi> the other of <hi>Tythes</hi> or <hi>Tenths,</hi> but with this <hi>difference,</hi> that they would have the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> the <hi>ſeventh part</hi> of <hi>time, conſecrate</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction</hi> from the <hi>reſt</hi> of <hi>time,</hi> which <hi>they ſay</hi> is <hi>allowed</hi> to <hi>men</hi> now as common, though the <hi>New Testament Sabbath</hi> not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166236:3"/>
without a <hi>Myſtery</hi> had its <hi>beginning</hi> on the <hi>eighth day</hi> (which was alſo the <hi>time</hi> of <hi>circumciſion,</hi> or the <hi>cutting off</hi> the <hi>fore-skin</hi> of the <hi>fleſh</hi>) to <hi>ſignifie,</hi> as <hi>Luther obſerves,</hi> that <hi>that day is</hi> of that <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>light,</hi> that <hi>after it</hi> no <hi>night</hi> ſhall <hi>follow:</hi> But as for that of <hi>Tythes,</hi> they ſpeak <hi>ambiguouſly,</hi> and <hi>ſeem</hi> to <hi>hold</hi> to it <hi>rather</hi> upon the <hi>account</hi> of <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> then as a right <hi>Divine</hi> of <hi>neceſſity</hi> to be <hi>bowed down to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Now I ſhall ſpeak my <hi>belief,</hi> and give my <hi>judgment</hi> as to both <hi>theſe,</hi> which is <hi>this,</hi> I <hi>like</hi> them <hi>both</hi> in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> which the <hi>Gentiles were,</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> are <hi>in;</hi> for it is <hi>far better</hi> that there be <hi>left</hi> ſome <hi>remembrances,</hi> of the <hi>right, title</hi> and <hi>intereſt God</hi> hath in both the <hi>perſons</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> and the <hi>times</hi> and <hi>things</hi> men are <hi>allowed</hi> to the <hi>uſe of,</hi> for <hi>his glory,</hi> then that <hi>all theſe,</hi> through <hi>Atheiſm, Pride, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> and <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> which <hi>raign</hi> and <hi>prevail</hi> ſo <hi>much</hi> all the <hi>world over,</hi> become wholy <hi>obliterate;</hi> yea upon one <hi>account</hi> I like better of the <hi>firſt</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> ſecond <hi>ſort, viz.</hi> thoſe that take more <hi>liberally</hi> of the <hi>uſages</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> both as <hi>touching</hi> the <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations</hi> of <hi>days,</hi> as having in <hi>uſe</hi> not only <hi>one day in ſeven,</hi> but <hi>days</hi> upon <hi>ſeveral accounts</hi> of <hi>Conſecration</hi> and <hi>Remembrance,</hi> yea <hi>whole weeks</hi> and <hi>years,</hi> which if they were <hi>true in</hi> but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>mind of God</hi> in thoſe <hi>things,</hi> as they were at firſt <hi>given</hi> of <hi>him</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>people,</hi> were of <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable uſe,</hi> as a <hi>Manuduction</hi> or <hi>Pedagogie</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> till the times of <hi>Deliverance</hi> ſhould <hi>come,</hi> through the <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as it did <hi>betide</hi> the <hi>former</hi> people, the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. But they <hi>having</hi> in theſe <hi>things</hi> (of great <hi>uſe</hi> in the firſt <hi>Inſtitution) corrupted themſelves,</hi> and are become <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> as well to the <hi>Law</hi> as to the <hi>Gospel,</hi> there hath <hi>aroſe</hi> out of <hi>them</hi> the <hi>people</hi> we call <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> but the <hi>other</hi> call <hi>them Hereticks,</hi> or <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> making ſome <hi>further adventure,</hi> more <hi>hopefully</hi> firſt in <hi>Luther,</hi> if we reſpect the <hi>Noiſe</hi> made at this <hi>ſudden rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> though <hi>there</hi> were at <hi>the ſame time ſome,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>one, affording,</hi> though with <hi>leſs obſervation</hi> as <hi>to moſt,</hi> a more <hi>clear light,</hi> and <hi>uniform,</hi> and of more <hi>uſe</hi> to all <hi>Nations,</hi> whoſe <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> hath <hi>yet been alone</hi> (as it were) <hi>heard</hi> in <hi>ſilence,</hi> this being <hi>overlooked,</hi> as the <hi>Truth</hi> in the <hi>full</hi> extent <hi>of it uſeth</hi> in all <hi>ages</hi> more or leſs <hi>to be; Comes Calvin,</hi> and others of <hi>great note</hi> with <hi>him,</hi> who ſeemed to <hi>build</hi> and attain <hi>higher</hi> then <hi>he</hi> that firſt <hi>lighted</hi> their <hi>Candle, Luther;</hi> yet their <hi>Superſtructure</hi> as it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166236:3"/>
proved <hi>ſince,</hi> being very <hi>ſpecious, had not, hath not</hi> enough of the <hi>foundation</hi> to <hi>perpetuate</hi> and <hi>uphold it, in ſo much</hi> that it <hi>ſhakes</hi> well nigh <hi>as much</hi> as what was in their <hi>account, Babel before,</hi> which they no <hi>ſooner perceived,</hi> but they were <hi>fain,</hi> as their <hi>Succeſſors ſince</hi> (therein evidently leaving their firſt <hi>Pattern</hi> and Example, <hi>Luther</hi>) to <hi>ſupport themſelves</hi> the ſame <hi>way</hi> did the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of <hi>Rome before,</hi> I mean by the <hi>weapons</hi> of this <hi>worlds warfare,</hi> as <hi>Impriſonments, Whippings,</hi> yea <hi>Burnings</hi> of men for a <hi>different belief,</hi> in the <hi>which</hi> all thoſe <hi>moſt excellent</hi> men, <hi>Calvin, Peter Martyr, Bucer,</hi> yea <hi>Beza</hi> heretofore <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors ſince,</hi> as we have ſeen in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland allowed,</hi> and is <hi>manifeſt</hi> in thoſe of the <hi>higheſt attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> I mean the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>New England,</hi> with whom doth <hi>concur</hi> thoſe in <hi>Old,</hi> or if <hi>not,</hi> why are they <hi>ſo ſilent</hi> in <hi>ſo great</hi> a <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>Conſequence</hi> as <hi>this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. So that the Sun ſetting in a ſort in a <hi>Cloud</hi> upon <hi>Calvin,</hi> but <hi>especially</hi> upon thoſe that would be <hi>thought</hi> his <hi>followers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> others</hi> have of late, eſpecially in this Land, made <hi>yet</hi> ſome <hi>adventure further</hi> (as we <hi>ſee</hi> at this day,) at the <hi>remove</hi> of which, all <hi>things,</hi> both <hi>fundamental, ſuperſtructural,</hi> and <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial,</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> are <hi>ſhattered,</hi> even <hi>quite</hi> almoſt to <hi>pieces,</hi> that <hi>there is,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>ſcarce</hi> ſo much as a <hi>ſheard</hi> left of this <hi>earthy pitcher,</hi> for <hi>any</hi> to take up a <hi>little water</hi> to <hi>refreſh himſelf therewithall;</hi> upon <hi>which opportunity</hi> is taken of the <hi>prophane ſpirit</hi> of <hi>worldlineſs, wickedneſs, ignorance</hi> and <hi>pride,</hi> to <hi>ruffle</hi> and come <hi>forth</hi> as <hi>Nimrod</hi> of <hi>old,</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> that with <hi>him</hi> would <hi>undertake</hi> to build a <hi>City</hi> and a <hi>Tower</hi> for <hi>themſelves,</hi> the <hi>top</hi> of <hi>which</hi> ſhould <hi>reach Heaven,</hi> and <hi>affront</hi> even <hi>God himſelf,</hi> for a <hi>ſecuring</hi> of <hi>themſelves</hi> in their <hi>luſts</hi> and <hi>evil:</hi> For as <hi>whiles</hi> there was an <hi>outcry</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Papiſts,</hi> many <hi>covetous worldlings,</hi> have <hi>well provided</hi> for them and <hi>theirs</hi> after <hi>them,</hi> with the <hi>ſpoils</hi> they took in that <hi>encounter:</hi> ſo the like occaſion <hi>ſince</hi> have here the <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> or rather <hi>thoſe</hi> that came in to their <hi>ayd,</hi> taken againſt their <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Task maſters,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops heretofore;</hi> ſo that what was <hi>left</hi> of the <hi>feathers</hi> of this <hi>ſo fair bird,</hi> theſe <hi>other birds</hi> of <hi>prey,</hi> have <hi>taken every</hi> one a <hi>part</hi> to <hi>themſelves;</hi> in ſo much the <hi>thing</hi> men call <hi>the Church,</hi> is <hi>become</hi> as in the <hi>day</hi> ſhe was <hi>firſt born,</hi> even in a <hi>manner</hi> a <hi>poor, despiſed</hi> and <hi>naked nothing,</hi> as to <hi>outward</hi> and <hi>worldly appearance,</hi> eſpecially if we <hi>conſider</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166236:4"/>
what is <hi>now laſt</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> in <hi>imitation</hi> of <hi>them</hi> that <hi>went before, purſued</hi> by all <hi>means</hi> to be <hi>brought to paſs, (i. e.)</hi> the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Glebe,</hi> through <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>covetouſneſs</hi> in a great <hi>degree detained</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and <hi>upon</hi> the ſame <hi>account</hi> (for the <hi>moſt part) ſought</hi> to be <hi>revokt</hi> of the <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. As to <hi>theſe</hi> things <hi>therefore</hi> its <hi>manifeſt,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have <hi>faln</hi> from the <hi>Goſpel Miniſtry</hi> and <hi>Converſation</hi> to that of the <hi>Old Law,</hi> where they <hi>ſecure themſelves</hi> as <hi>well</hi> as they <hi>can,</hi> ſo are we the <hi>Proteſtants here faln</hi> in <hi>appearance (which</hi> I <hi>deſire</hi> the <hi>Reader</hi> to <hi>obſerve</hi>) a <hi>degree lower,</hi> and <hi>ſomewhat</hi> nearer the <hi>Earth,</hi> having let <hi>go</hi> our <hi>hold</hi> even of the <hi>Law it ſelf,</hi> and the <hi>things</hi> and <hi>uſages in it,</hi> and are <hi>now become,</hi> to the <hi>wonder</hi> of all the <hi>world, inſtead</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> being <hi>faln from Rome,</hi> as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> to an imitation (as ſome <hi>would have it</hi>) of <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Heathen;</hi> to reach which <hi>Politicus</hi> makes no ſmall ado: <hi>This,</hi> as the <hi>Lord</hi> is <hi>witneſs,</hi> I <hi>ſpeak not</hi> to <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid</hi> or <hi>vilifie</hi> him, much leſs <hi>either</hi> the <hi>perſons</hi> or the <hi>attainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> the <hi>perſons</hi> upholding the <hi>preſent Power</hi> have <hi>reacht unto,</hi> but (as <hi>having</hi> them in great <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>eſteem,</hi> and <hi>judging</hi> with <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>with all my heart confeſſing,</hi> that I had <hi>rather a thouſand fold</hi> live in a <hi>Heathen Commonwealth,</hi> then <hi>in</hi> or <hi>under</hi> an <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church,</hi> in <hi>which</hi> by <hi>ſearch</hi> will be <hi>found</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>all</hi> that have <hi>been ſlain</hi> upon the <hi>Earth,</hi> I (ſeeking the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>ancient,</hi> and <hi>that I ſay not the only glory</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> of this our <hi>Native Land) would</hi> the Government <hi>of it</hi> ſhould be <hi>given up</hi> of <hi>a ready mind</hi> to <hi>him whoſe right it is, the Lords; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I,</hi> and for that <hi>end</hi> I make <hi>continual prayer</hi> and <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>Rulers ſhould manage</hi> or <hi>meddle</hi> with the <hi>Affairs</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> but <hi>in the Name,</hi> and <hi>the alone Authority of him, whoſe all the Kingdoms of the world are,</hi> and <hi>who is even now the ſecond time entring upon his own Inheritance,</hi> as <hi>the right Heir of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Here then would be <hi>found</hi> (in the <hi>third</hi> place) a <hi>view</hi> of the <hi>third</hi> and beſt <hi>ſort</hi> of <hi>People</hi> the whole <hi>Earth affords,</hi> which in the Scripture <hi>phraſe</hi> are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> or the <hi>Lords true anointed ones, which I for my part,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> and others <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, judg alone meet</hi> to be <hi>likened</hi> to the <hi>third,</hi> and <hi>moſt inward part</hi> of the <hi>Temple, (was</hi> form'd of <hi>Solomon,</hi> according to the Pattern was ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David</hi> on the <hi>Mount</hi> with <hi>God,</hi>) which was <hi>ſaid to be</hi> the <hi>place,</hi> as theſe <hi>are the people, moſt holy: Theſe</hi> are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166236:4"/>
               <hi>thoſe</hi> that <hi>have ceaſed</hi> from <hi>their own works,</hi> even as <hi>God did</hi> from <hi>his,</hi> and have <hi>nought</hi> elſe <hi>now</hi> to <hi>do,</hi> but to ſing Hymns to God in a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>righteous life</hi> towards <hi>him</hi> and <hi>men</hi> for <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more;</hi> here is <hi>found,</hi> and <hi>had indeed,</hi> the <hi>reſtitution</hi> of <hi>all things, ſpoken of</hi> by <hi>all the holy Prophets</hi> that <hi>have been</hi> ever <hi>ſince</hi> the world <hi>began; here</hi> they <hi>neither marry,</hi> or are <hi>bound</hi> in <hi>heart</hi> or <hi>life</hi> to <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> nor are given in <hi>marriage</hi> in that <hi>ſence</hi> to any <hi>creature, Angel, man,</hi> or <hi>thing,</hi> but are as the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>God, i. e.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">For here <hi>alone</hi> is the <hi>Apoſtles Rule</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29. <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</hi>
               </note> whether in wedlock or ſingle life, living <hi>wholy holily, purely</hi> and <hi>chaſtly</hi> to <hi>him</hi> that ſits upon the <hi>Throne, as King</hi> &amp; <hi>Law giver in their hearts;</hi> in one <hi>word,</hi> all that <hi>herein is, is become moſt holy, pure, juſt</hi> and <hi>good, every</hi> thing is becom <hi>conſecrate,</hi> even the <hi>very bells</hi> and <hi>bridles</hi> of the <hi>Horſes,</hi> have <hi>writ</hi> upon them <hi>what was wont only</hi> to be on the <hi>forehead</hi> of the <hi>High Prieſt, Holineſs to the Lord; no man here</hi> (as in the <hi>Apoſtles times) calls</hi> or <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts</hi> any <hi>thing</hi> at <hi>all his own,</hi> it being <hi>as much</hi> and as <hi>truly</hi> his <hi>neighbors,</hi> as <hi>his,</hi> yea <hi>rather</hi> it is <hi>alone the Lords, all that's there,</hi> and <hi>no man enjoys ought but in the alone right of him;</hi> yet <hi>all</hi> according to <hi>the moſt holy Law of God</hi> was <hi>given by Moſes,</hi> for the <hi>true body of Moſes</hi> is <hi>here</hi> found in <hi>ſpirit (underſtanding</hi> it of the people that <hi>beleeve</hi>) the <hi>true body of Jeſus,</hi> in whom the <hi>whole Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> hath <hi>its end, mind,</hi> and <hi>fulfilling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Now <hi>though I</hi> for my <hi>part believe,</hi> that all theſe <hi>late</hi> and <hi>preſent ſhakings,</hi> as well of <hi>things heavenly</hi> in <hi>their nature</hi> and <hi>kind,</hi> as <hi>earthly, tend</hi> to <hi>this</hi> as their <hi>proper reſt</hi> and <hi>center;</hi> yet I would in <hi>this,</hi> as <hi>declare</hi> my <hi>deſire,</hi> ſo <hi>put to</hi> my <hi>helping</hi> hand, to <hi>prevent</hi> and <hi>ſtave off,</hi> the <hi>firſt ſort of men</hi> and <hi>people</hi> of <hi>Gentile heart</hi> and <hi>converſation,</hi> that they lay <hi>not,</hi> as <hi>they are</hi> apt to <hi>do</hi> their <hi>hands</hi> on the <hi>ſacred Signs, Types</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> in <hi>uſe</hi> to <hi>them</hi> of the <hi>ſecond ſort,</hi> who <hi>anſwering</hi> to the <hi>middle part</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> are as yet <hi>under the Law,</hi> or <hi>letter only</hi> of <hi>divine things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Wherefore</hi> in <hi>particular</hi> as <hi>concerning Tythes,</hi> let it be <hi>made</hi> or <hi>put</hi> into a <hi>Decree throughout theſe three Nations,</hi> now <hi>under</hi> and <hi>in</hi> the diſpoſe of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> that <hi>all the goods</hi> heretofore <hi>counted ſeparate</hi> or <hi>ſacred,</hi> that are <hi>yet left undiſpoſed</hi> or <hi>ſold,</hi> be <hi>left</hi> and <hi>reckoned</hi> as the <hi>right of God,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>according</hi> to their primitive <hi>inſtitution</hi> under <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>donation ſince,</hi> under <hi>ſeveral Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes;</hi> by <hi>both which</hi> it will <hi>appear,</hi> as <hi>John Wickliff (worthy</hi> of <hi>honorable eſteem</hi> and <hi>memory,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:166236:5"/>
as in <hi>all Lands,</hi> ſo <hi>eſpecially</hi> in this our <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi>) proves at <hi>large,</hi> that they are <hi>no other</hi> then <hi>the free alms of the people, which</hi> they were <hi>originally willing</hi> to <hi>allow,</hi> as their <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments</hi> of <hi>Gods right</hi> to <hi>all</hi> they <hi>had,</hi> I ſay, to <hi>allow him</hi> in <hi>thoſe</hi> that he <hi>hath</hi> (as is <hi>confest throughout the Scripture</hi>) a <hi>more immediate care of,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>poor,</hi> among which the <hi>Levite,</hi> as the <hi>ſteward</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in this <hi>behalf, is reckoned,</hi> having no <hi>other</hi> then the <hi>Lord</hi> for his <hi>portion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. And <hi>let</hi> it be <hi>added</hi> with this <hi>clauſe,</hi> that <hi>he,</hi> what <hi>ever he</hi> be <hi>called</hi> in every <hi>Town</hi> or <hi>Pariſh,</hi> whether <hi>Parſon, Rector, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, Miniſter, Priest, Preſbyter,</hi> or <hi>Lecturer,</hi> do not in <hi>time</hi> to <hi>come</hi> lay <hi>claim</hi> to any of <hi>theſe goods</hi> in his <hi>own name,</hi> but <hi>alone</hi> in the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>poor,</hi> whoſe <hi>right</hi> from <hi>men,</hi> by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> he <hi>is,</hi> but <hi>without force,</hi> to <hi>plead</hi> and <hi>contend for,</hi> according to the <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>most holy Law</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. And <hi>laſtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> That <hi>here,</hi> and from <hi>hence,</hi> all that are in <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> all that are in <hi>want,</hi> the <hi>poor, lame,</hi> and <hi>blind,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> that are <hi>neceſſitous</hi> (but <hi>none</hi> that are <hi>wilfully</hi> or <hi>wickedly idle,</hi> and of <hi>evil life</hi>) may have <hi>ſome proportionable ſupport,</hi> as <hi>out</hi> of the <hi>Treaſury and Store-houſes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Land, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed</hi> to <hi>be ſuch</hi> by a <hi>decree</hi> from the <hi>chief Powers in it: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this</hi> I will be bold to <hi>conclude,</hi> in the <hi>ſame ſpirit</hi> and <hi>mend</hi> to this <hi>Nation,</hi> as <hi>Malachy</hi> or the <hi>Meſſenger of God</hi> did of <hi>old</hi> to that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Bring ye all the Tythes into the <hi>Store-houſe,</hi> that there may be meat in my houſe, and prove me now here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, if I will not open you the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Heaven, and pour you out a bleſſing, that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it. <hi>And I will rebuke the devourer for your ſakes, and he ſhall not destroy the fruits of your ground, neither ſhall your vine caſt her fruit before the time in the field, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. And all Nations ſhall call you bleſſed, for ye ſhall be a delightſom Land, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the black ſpread Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
